A Guide to the Papers of Gertrude Stein, 1907-1955, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Gertrude Stein, 1907-1955, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
8259, -a, -b, -c, -d, -e
This collection consists of ca. 103 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
8259: Deposit, December 17, 1963. Gift, July 1, 1991; 8259-a: Gift, July 9, 1985; 8259-b: Gift, July 12, 1989; 8259-c: Purchase, November 30, 2000; 8259-d: Purchase, May 9, 2001; 8259-e: Archival transfer, May 27, 2003; 9924-b: Gift, February 12, 1975.
Biographical Information
Gertrude Stein (b. Feb. 3, 1874, Allegheny, Pa., U.S.--d. July 27, 1946, Paris), was an avant-garde American writer, eccentric, and self-styled genius, whose Paris home was a salon for the leading artists and writers of the period between World Wars I and II.
Stein spent her infancy in Vienna and Paris and her girlhood in Oakland, Calif. At Radcliffe College she studied psychology with the philosopher William James. After further study at Johns Hopkins medical school she went to Paris, where she was able to live by private means. From 1903 to 1912 she lived with her brother Leo, who became an accomplished art critic; thereafter she lived with her lifelong companion Alice B. Toklas (1877-1967).
Stein and her brother were among the first collectors of works by the Cubists and other experimental painters of the period, such as Pablo Picasso (who painted her portrait), Henri Matisse, and Georges Braque, several of whom became her friends. At her salon they mingled with expatriate American writers, such as Sherwood Anderson and Ernest Hemingway, and other visitors drawn by her literary reputation. Her literary and artistic judgments were revered, and her chance remarks could make or destroy reputations. In her own work, she attempted to parallel the theories of Cubism, specifically in her concentration on the illumination of the present moment and her use of slightly varied repetitions and extreme simplification and fragmentation. The best explanation of her theory of writing is found in the essay Composition and Explanation, which is based on lectures that she gave at the universities of Oxford and Cambridge and was issued as a book in 1926. Among her work that was most thoroughly influenced by Cubism is Tender Buttons (1914), which carries fragmentation and abstraction beyond the borders of intelligibility.
Her first published book, Three Lives (1909), the stories of three working-class women, has been called a minor masterpiece. The Making of Americans, a long composition written in 1906-1908 but not published until 1925, was too convoluted and obscure for general readers, for whom she remained essentially the author of such lines as "A rose is a rose is a rose is a rose." Her only book to reach a wide public was The Autobiography of Alice B. Toklas (1933), actually Stein's own autobiography. The performance in the United States of her Four Saints in Three Acts (1934), which the composer Virgil Thomson had made into an opera, led to a triumphal American lecture tour in 1934-1935. Thomson also wrote the music for her second opera, The Mother of Us All (published 1947), based on the life of feminist Susan B. Anthony.
Stein became a legend in Paris, especially after surviving the German occupation of France and befriending the many young American servicemen who visited her. She wrote about these soldiers in Brewsie and Willie (1946).
Scope and Content
Series I, literary manuscripts, consists exclusively of manuscripts about Gertrude Stein by others, most notably Alice B. Toklas and Sherwood Anderson. Sherwood Anderson's "The work of Gertrude Stein" appeared as the introduction to Stein's Geography and Plays published in 1922.
Correspondence, the second series, is an eclectic mix of letters that displays many facets of Gertrude Stein's character. Ranging from demanding prompt and timely payments from publishers to the fostering of artistic talents, Stein displays her unique and distinctive writing style. Correspondents include M. A. Agelasto, Edmund R. Brown, Lt. Jean Deurel, Pierre de Massot, Sir Francis Rose, William Seabrook, and Virgil Thomson. Also included in correspondence are letters by Alice B. Toklas. Acting as Gertrude Stein's secretary and amanuensis, many of her letters simply relay Stein's ideas or concerns. In 1955 Toklas was asked to contribute an article about Henri Matisse to the Yale Literary Magazine and her correspondence concerning this article is included.
The third series, Miscellaneous Documents, includes the official book contracts for Stein's Geography and Plays, initially published by The Four Seas Company in 1922 but later transferred to Bruce Humphries, Inc. in 1930. Also included is a scrapbook compiled by Edna Kenton, which includes various photographs and articles about Gertrude Stein along with published stories by Sherwood Anderson.
Photographs of Gertrude Stein constitute the fourth and final series. Many of the photographs are of her visit to the University of Virginia in 1935. Included with Stein are such figures as Alice B. Toklas, A.G.A. Balz, Scott Buchanan, Carl Van Vechten, Anna Barringer, Emily Clark Balch, James Southall Wilson, and John Cook Wyllie.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series. Series I, literary manuscripts, is arranged alphabetically by title; Series II, correspondence, is sub-arranged as the correspondence of Gertrude Stein (subseries A) and the correspondence of Alice B. Toklas (subseries B); both subseries are arranged alphabetically by correspondent; Series III, miscellaneous documents; and Series IV, photographs and prints, which is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Series I: Literary Manuscripts
  - "Commentary on Gertrude Stein's Geography and Plays," by [Alice B. Toklas], AMs, 1 p. #8259. (Box-folder 1:1)
  - "Gertrude Stein from Three Lives to Geography and Plays," by Edna Kenton, n.d., TMs, 2 copies with textual variations. #8259-e. (Box-folder 1:2)
  - "Some Memories of Henri Matisse (1907-1922)," by Alice B. Toklas AMsS, [1955 February 15], 5 pp. on 5 l.; with envelope. #8259. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Includes accompanying letter (1 p.) from Alice B. Toklas to Editor of Yale Literary Magazine, 1955 February 15.
  - "The Work of Gertrude Stein," by Sherwood Anderson, n.d., TMs with autograph revisions, 4 pp. on 4 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Published as the Introduction to Geography and Plays, 1922.
- Series II: Correspondence
  - Subseries A: Correspondence of Gertrude Stein
    - Bruce Humphries, Inc. to Alice B. Toklas, 1935 June 18, TL, carbon, 1 p. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:5)
      Bruce Humphries, Inc. responds to Toklas' complaints about statements for Geography and Plays.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1922 January 24, TLS, 3 pp. on 3 l.; with autograph corrections. #8259. (Box-folder 1:6)
      Stein discusses translation rights for her new book [Geography and Plays]. Asks Edmund Brown to write to Sherwood Anderson and inform him when they need his preface to her book.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1922 March 2, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l.; with autograph corrections. #8259. (Box-folder 1:7)
      Stein approves of the changes in her book [Geography and Plays] and also is "pleased" with Sherwood Anderson's introduction. Stein would like better samples for the cloth of the binding of the book.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1922 May 11, TLS, 3 pp. on 3 l.; with autograph corrections. #8259. (Box-folder 1:8)
      Stein is happy with the corrections of the book [Geography and Plays] but still has a few corrections to make. She mentions that the "errors are small but the correction of them is very important." Photographs of Stein by Man Ray may be useful for publicity.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1922 July 10, TLS, 3 pp. on 3 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:9)
      Stein has completely corrected the proofs for [Geography and Plays]. Sends list (not included) of people to send advance notices of book. It is "very important" that these people receive advance notices before the book goes out on the market. Mentions sculptor Jo Davidson doing a bust of her, which will be good for publicity.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1922 September 9, LS, 2 p. on 2 l.; in the hand of Alice B. Toklas, signed by Stein. #8259. (Box-folder 1:10)
      Stein discusses the type of lettering for the side paper and the shelf back for [Geography and Plays]. Her corrections are "novel and effective."
    - [Gertrude Stein] to [Edmund R.] Brown, 1922 October 23, L, 2 p. on 2 l.; in the hand of Alice B. Toklas. #8259. (Box-folder 1:11)
      Stein discusses the details for distribution of Geography and Plays throughout the world.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edmund R.] Brown, [ca. 1922], TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:12)
      Writing to the Four Seas Publishing Company because all her past publishers have been "men who while they may have increased my public have not dealt fairly with me." She will be honored to have Geography and Plays, her fifth book, published by Four Seas.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edmund R.] Brown, [ca. 1922], TLS, 4 pp. on 4 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:13)
      Stein is flattered that Brown read her manuscript for Geography and Plays and also flattered that he is interested in her method of writing. She writes: "My style has been a gradual development from The Three Lives written in 1905 through a series of studies and experiments for the freer and more profound feeling for words, studies which really take us back to the Elizabethans who also had the joy of discovering pleasure in words." Stein then provides ideas for the "manufacturing and marketing" of the book.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1923 February 4, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.; with autograph corrections. #8259. (Box-folder 1:14)
      Stein is "very pleased" with the appearance of Geography and Plays. Sends two copies (not included) of Man Ray photographs.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1923 March 6, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:15)
      Inquires about the sales and success of Geography and Plays. Asks that the statements be sent to her. Mentions the various photographs and articles, one by Miss Edna Kenton, that will aid in her publicity.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1923 May 10, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:16)
      Further inquires about sales of Geography and Plays, and states that this information is crucial for her French income tax.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1923 May 14, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.; with autograph corrections. #8259. (Box-folder 1:17)
      Discusses articles written about her in reference to Geography and Plays, including articles by Jane Burr, Mina Loy, and Max Bryde. Indicates that this will help in her new book which she is "busily working at."
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1923 July 10, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:18)
      Acknowledges reports of success of Geography and Plays, and would like royalty statements that she has yet to receive.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1923 September 15, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:19)
      Requires that statement of sales be sent to her every three months. Curious as to why the general tone of the reviews of Geography and Plays has been changing, and notes how Mr. Menken includes Stein "among the list of the ten dullest authors."
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1924 January 27, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:20)
      Tells Edmund Brown that she is submitting "Miss Furr and Miss Skeene" into a collection of short stories edited by Miss Frances Newman. Also mentions reference to her work in "A Love Story" published in the September issue of Cosmopolitan. Asks that there is no delay in sending her the statement and cheque due February 1 and that five copies of Geography and Plays be sent to her.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1924 April 23, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l.; with autograph corrections. #8259. (Box-folder 1:21)
      Reiterates that there can be no delay in sending her the statements and that she should not have been charged for the five copies of Geography and Plays sent to her.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1924 November 22, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:22)
      Mentions "very laudatory" article in the October issue of Vogue on Geography and Plays and the November issue of Punch devoted to Mina Loy's article. Asks that the October statement and cheque be sent immediately.
    - Gertrude Stein to Dr. [Johnston], [ca. 1924], ANS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:23)
      Tells Dr. Johnston that he figures in one of her pieces "An Indian Bay" published in "The Reviewer." Stationary includes "Rose is a rose is a rose" embossing. The issue of "The Reviewer" in question published in January, 1924.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1925 March 1, TLS, 2 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:24)
      Asks that more copies of Geography and Plays be distributed for sale. Interest in her book in England requires that the book be available for purchase.
    - Gertrude Stein to Mrs. Harry A. Coleman, 1925 March 22, TLS, 1 p. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:25)
      Turns down invitation to attend the Authors' Congress in Washington, DC, but appreciates that her book will be in the book section of the Book Fair.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Edumnd R.] Brown, 1925 May 29, TLS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:26)
      Stein writes that she gave Brown's proposition regarding The Making of Americans to Robert Mac Almon of the Contact Publishing Company, but he politely declined. Reiterates that the statement and cheque for Geography and Plays is long overdue.
    - Gertrude [Stein] to Pierre de Massot, [1930 May 14], APCS, 1 item. #8259. (Box-folder 1:27)
      Stein pleased that de Massot did a preface to her book. Mentions that the "chief occupation in the country the month of May" is "getting wet and getting dry again."
    - Gertrude Stein to [Pierre] de Massot, [ca. 1930], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:28)
      Thanks de Massot for the "little book" which she enjoyed.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Pierre] de Massot, [ca. 1930], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:29)
      Stein tells de Massot that it will be a pleasure to see him again some day. Stationary includes "Rose is a rose is a rose" embossing.
    - Gertrude [Stein] to [Pierre de Massot], [ca. 1930], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:30)
      Stein hopes de Massot is not ill and invites him to tea Sunday. Stationary includes "Rose is a rose is a rose" embossing.
    - Gertrude [Stein] to Pierre [de Massot], [ca. 1930], ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:31)
      Looking forward to seeing de Massot in September when they are in the country.
    - Gertrude [Stein] to Pierre [de Massot], [ca. 1930], ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:32)
      Stein just received de Massot's preface and praises de Massot's writing, in particular his use of quotations: "I don't quite know what you do with them. They cease to [e]xist in your use of them and yet they are there as [position?]." Stein is "looking forward enormously to the Bulldog."
    - Gertrude [Stein] to Pierre [de Massot], [ca. 1930], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:33)
      Invites de Massot to stay with them. Will be pleased if he translates Tender Buttons.
    - Gertrude [Stein] to Pierre [de Massot], [ca. 1930], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with envelope and wax seal. #8259. (Box-folder 1:34)
      Invites de Massot over on Friday. It would please Stein if de Massot would do the "introduction." Stationary includes "Rose is a rose is a rose" embossing.
    - Gertrude Stein to Pierre [de Massot], [ca. 1930], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:35)
      Stein just finished reading "Bull Dog" which deeply moved her. Stein writes: "Yours is the only beautiful writing of any one beside my own of anybody living." She is looking forward to seeing him again.
    - Gertrude [Stein] to Pierre [de Massot], [ca. 1930], ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:36)
      Stein is looking forward to seeing de Massot in September. Stein mentions that she is working on a translation that "has turned out interesting in many ways." Also wants to do something with the "three leaf clover."
    - Gertrude Stein to Sir Francis Rose, [1931 November 26], ANS, 1 p. on 1 l.; with envelope. #8259. (Box-folder 1:37)
      Invites Sir Francis Rose to tea on Sunday. Stationary includes "Rose is a rose is a rose" embossing.
    - Gertrude Stein to M. A. Agelasto, [1934 November 11], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l., with envelope. #9924-b. (Box-folder 1:38)
      Wants accounts of the performance of the opera. Quotes from her Composition as Explanation: "...to make everybody see the beauty, and once they see the beauty they see nothing else, and so one does appreciate those who saw before they saw the beauty."
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], [ca. 1935], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l., with envelope. #8259. (Box-folder 1:39)
      Has faith in Rose as a painter and tells him, "like all of us you have to live through a great deal."
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], [ca. 1936], ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:40)
      Advises Rose to stick with the art dealer Pierre Colle who, although not completely interested in Rose's work, at least has them and will show them on request. Hints of the Spanish Revolution: "The Spanish revolution is xciting [sic] almost anything is xciting [sic]."
    - Gertrude [Stein] to Lt. Jean Deurel, 1945 May 11, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:41)
      Tells Deurel that Charbot sent 10,000 francs which she will not cash without proper accounting. Stein will cash check from Fontaine. In French with English translation.
    - Gertrude [Stein] to Lt. Jean Deurel, [1945 September 15], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l.; with envelope. #8259. (Box-folder 1:42)
      Explains that her two books, The Wars I Have Seen and Three Lives are arranged with Charbot. In French with English translation.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Cernchild ?], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:43)
      Having just returned to Paris, Stein fondly remembers [?], which they completely loved. Just met Colette and her new husband, and is surprised that he hasn't met them yet.
    - Gertrude Stein to "My dear Potter," n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with typed transcription. #8259. (Box-folder 1:44)
      Thanks Mr. Potter for accommodating her in her lectures, which demands that there be an audience of only 500.
    - Gertrude Stein to "Mr. Potter," n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with typed transcription. #8259. (Box-folder 1:45)
      Stein is working very hard on the lectures she is to give at Columbia, although it would be "pleasanter if there were more of them given at one place."
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir Francis Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:46)
      Suggests a short visit in the country to see how he likes it, and for a longer stay later on. Tells him that the accommodations are simple: "no bath-rooms, no luxuries, but it is rather lovely..."
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir Francis Rose], n.d., ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:47)
      Stein suggests Rose keep painting and not worry about gallery politics, and describes at length the pleasure his pictures have given a local French family who saw them at her home.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], n.d., ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:48)
      Stein is angered because Rose wants to exchange a painting he gave to her for another, because a gallery would rather have Stein's. She refuses to exchange the picture. Even his asking to exchange a picture shows a "lack of courtesy" that is foreign to his nature. Ends letter by giving him some advice, "that everything you do should be something directly conceived, for good or for bad."
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir Francis Rose], n.d., ALS, 6 pp. on 3 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:49)
      Offers advice regarding which galleries to show his paintings. Mentions two of his paintings: "the two old heads" and "the gray nude against the greenish background., the latter being inspired by the little statues he sent her.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir Francis Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:50)
      In one continuous sentence, Stein relates information about Waldeman and the article he is writing, her difficult financial situation, and how they may "all be with bycicles [sic] sadly with bycicles [sic]."
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:51)
      Discusses the photographs of Miss Toklas [probably for the book The Autobiography of Alice B. Toklas], about which Stein is very pleased.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir Francis Rose], n.d., ALS, 3 pp. on 3 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:52)
      Worried something misfortunate happened to Rose. Invites Rose to visit them Saturday and he could return on Monday.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir Francis Rose], n.d., ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:53)
      Advises Rose not to send more than three paintings to show, as they "will be gone for such a very long time." Suggests going to the "baths" in Aix in order to help his ailing arm. Mentions Basket and Bayun.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir Francis Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:54)
      Wishes Rose a "nice Christmas" and a "happy new year." Thanks Rose for the drawings he gave them and looks forward to seeing him in the spring. Tells him that "Santa Clause was nice to Basket." Stationary includes "Rose is a rose is a rose" embossing.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir Francis Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:55)
      Concerned about Basket's [eczema ?] while he is at the vet's, whom they telephone every day. Looking forward to seeing Rose soon, and that Basket will be happier and better by then.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir Francis Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:56)
      Advises Rose to write to clear up the confusion regarding the galleries which want to show his paintings. Stein would like to see his new pictures but is concerned that they will not be properly crated for the return since there is no one she trusts who can do it properly.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir Francis Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:57)
      Stein is worried about the health of Curley, Rose's dog. Mentions the painting "the little seven year old" which Stein thinks is very lovely.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir] Francis [Rose], n.d., ALS, 4 pp. on 4 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:58)
      Indicates that she will do something very important for Rose's future. She succeeded in getting the most important artist dealer in Paris interested in Rose's work who will plan a show with his landscapes. Stein promised to lend them "Belgium" and "the waterfall" for the show. However, Stein makes it clear that this dealer will not work with anyone but Rose in the transaction. Stein ends with "I think it's a big chance for you."
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir Francis Rose], n.d., ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:59)
      Stein enjoyed spending time with Rose, and each time they get to "know each other a little more." Tells Rose that there is a good view from St. Remy that would make a good landscape, "which is the nearest thing to a chinese landscape in miniature that xsits [sic] in Europe." Basket is feeling better.
    - Gertrude Stein to [Sir Francis Rose], n.d., ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8259. (Box-folder 1:60)